[Music]
suppose that a b c and d are all
positive real numbers and that a over b
is less than c over d the line
connecting the origin to the point b a
has a slope of a over b
the line connecting the origin and the
point dc has a slope c over d
therefore by assumption the line
connecting 0 0 to b a has a slope that's
less than the slope of the line
connecting 0 0 to d c
let's connect the points b over a and d
over c with a line and then highlight
the midpoint between these two points
the x coordinate of this midpoint is
halfway between b and d and the y
coordinate of this point is halfway
between a and c so the coordinates of
this point are given by b plus d over 2
a plus c over 2.
the line connecting the origin to this
point lies between the first two lines
we started with
therefore the slope of the line
connecting 0 0 to b a is less than the
slope of the line connecting 0 0 to the
midpoint and that is less than the slope
of the line connecting 0 0 to dc
as we've already seen the slope of the
line connecting 0 0 to b a is a over b
the slope of the line connecting 0 0 to
d c is c over d and now we can check
that the slope of the line connecting 0
0 to the midpoint is a plus c over b
plus d
therefore the condition that a over b is
less than c over d implies that a over b
is less than a plus c over b plus d
which is less than c over d
the fraction a plus c over b plus d is
the median of a over b and c over d and
this inequality is known as the mediant
inequality
you